Good morning. Today's דף daf. *daf* is קו *Kuf Vav*. We are
still in the מלכי *malchei* portion of the פרק חלק Perek Chelek
*Perek Chelek*. We have moved on from the three מלכים *melachim* that
don't have a portion in the world to come to the four
commoners that do not. We've been focusing on בלעם Bilam *Bilaam*,
and we pick up with let's go, וישם דבר בפי בלעם Bilam
*Vayasem Davar Bephi Bilam*. It's about 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 11 lines
from the bottom exactly in the middle of the line with a
little circle there. וישם דבר בפי בלעם Bilam *Vayasem Davar Bephi Bilam*:
God placed a word in the mouth of בלעם Bilam *Bilaam*. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* אומר *omer*: מלאך *malach*, an angel was
sort of put, given with him to I guess instruct him what
to say. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* אמר amar *amar*: חכה *chaka*, a
what do you call it? Like a hook. Like a fishhook, God
dragged him. הגר"א *the Gra* says that these don't really contradict. One
is speaking about, like if you got a hook in a fish's
mouth, it can't like open its mouth, or it can't get its
tongue out of its mouth if you have like the angel, or
another version had it was a bit or something like sort of
forces its tongue out. Anyway, הגר"א *the Gra* says sort of the
idea is that one of these is preventing him saying what he
wanted to say, and the other is getting him saying the right
thing. אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan, *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*: מברכתו של
אותו רשע *Mibeichaso shel oso rasha*, from the blessing of that wicked
person, אתה למד מה היה haya בלבו *ata lamed ma haya belibo*,
you can figure out, just do the reverse and you can figure
out what he wanted to say to curse us. Okay, because God
reversed it.
So, ביקש לומר שלא יהיו להם בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות *Bikesh lomar
shelo yehu lahem batei knesiyos u'batei midrashot*. He wanted to say we
should not have synagogues and study halls. מה טובו אהליך יעקב *Ma
Tovu Ohalecha Yaakov*: how glorious, how beautiful are your tents, oh Jacob.
So he obviously wanted to say the exact opposite. לא תשרה שכינה
עליהם *Lo tishreh shechinah aleihem*: and he wanted to say that God's
divine presence shouldn't rest on them. משכנותיך ישראל Yisrael *Mishkenotecha Yisrael*: your
dwelling places, but here from also the word שכינה *shechinah*, where God
dwells, right, is beautiful. לא תהא מלכותם נמשכת *Lo tehei malchusum nimshaches*:
he wanted to say that our kingship, the kingdom should not be
extended like be a long time. כנחלים נטיו *Kenachalim nitayu*: like rivers
that are stretched out. Rivers, the imagery of kingship. לא יהא להם
זיתים וכרמים *Lo yehei lahem zeisim u'keramim*: that we should not have
olives and vineyards, olive trees and vineyards. כגנות עלי נהר *Keganos alei
nahar*: like gardens by the river. לא יהא ריחו נודף *Lo yehei
reicho nodef*: let their aroma not be aromatic, not be sort of
wafting, which also could be metaphoric. לא יהא כאהלים נטע ה' *Lo
yehei k'ahalim nata Hashem*: like
אהלים *ahalim*, which I think the point here is an אהל *ohel*
could be obviously a tent and that fits with the word נטע
*nata*, to plant, but אהל *ohel* is also a type of an
aromatic fragrance.
What is it? מור ואהלות *mor ve'ahalot*. So I think that's how
it's being read here. לא יהא להם מלכים בעלי קומה *Lo yehei
lahem melachim ba'alei komah*: that we should not have kings that are
of stature, I guess physical and otherwise. כארזים עלי מים *Kearazim alei
mayim*: like cedar trees by the water. לא יהא מלך בן מלך
*Lo yehei melech ben melech*: we should not have a king the
son of a king, right? It should not be like a kingship,
a royal family. יזל מים מדליו *Yizal mayim midalyav*: let the water
flow from their buckets, so the sense of one coming from the
next. לא תהא מלכותם שולטת באומות *Lo tehei malchusum sholetes ba'umos*: he
wanted to say that it should not have kingship over the other
nations, dominion. וזרעו במים רבים *Vezaro bemayim rabim*: his descendants over many
waters. לא תהא עזה מלכותם *Lo tehei azah malchusum*: it should not
be powerful. וירם מאגג מלכו *Veyarom meAgag malko*: their king will be
greater than Agag. לא תהא אימת מלכותם *Lo tehei eimas malchusum*: there
should not be, or their kingship should not be fearful. ותנשא מלכותו
*Vetinesa malchuso*: let the kingship be lifted up. Okay, so basically just
reverse it all. So in the course of this, a lot of
these metaphors are not explained. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is also
explaining or taking his take on what the metaphors mean and also
letting us, we can infer, like he wanted to say the opposite.
Because the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says ויהפוך ה' אלוהיך לך את הקללה
לברכה *Vayafoch Hashem Elokecha lach es hakelalah libracha*, God reversed it. So
if you want to understand what he wanted to say, just take
the ברכה bracha, *bracha* and reverse it. Okay. אמר רבי אבא בר
כהנא Amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana, *Amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana*: כולם
חזרו לקללה *Kulam chazru leklalah*. Unfortunately, all of the negative stuff eventually
came true. Did it come true because he wanted to say it?
Did it come true
because of our sins it would have come true anyway? But it's
an interesting question, even though he didn't articulate it, his thoughts actually
do eventually materialize when we sinned. Right, if you think about it,
we currently don't have a kingship. 80 percent of that was about
kingship. We're no longer in the land of Israel with these beautiful
olive trees and vineyards, etc., etc. Okay, so כולם חזרו לקללה *kulam
chazru leklalah*.
In the end they all reverted to their original intentional curse, חוץ
מבתי כנסיות ומבתי מדרשות *chutz mi'batei knesiyos u'mibatei midrashot*, except for the
very first one, the מה טובו אהליך יעקב *Ma Tovu Ohalecha Yaakov*.
Because no matter where we are, no matter how much we're in
exile, we still have synagogues and study halls. שנאמר shenemar ויהפוך ה'
אלוהיך לך את הקללה לברכה *Shene'emar Vayafoch Hashem Elokecha lach es hakelalah
libracha*: God reversed the curse to a blessing, כי אהבך ה' אלוהיך
*ki ahevecha Hashem Elokecha*, because God loves you. קללה ולא קללות *Kelalah
velo kelalot*: He only reversed like, so only one of them remained
a blessing. The other of them they, in the end, they reverted
to being a קללות *kelalot*, but one. אמר ר׳ שמואל Shmuel, בר
נחמני אמר ר׳ יונתן מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv what’s meant by the
verse, נאמנים פצעי אוהב neemanim pitzei ohev trustworthy are the wounds of
a beloved, ונעתרות
נשיקות שונא venaatarot neshikot soneh and changing like
unreliable are the kisses of an enemy. So you know, טובה קללה
שקילל אחיה השילוני את ישראל יותר מברכה שבירכם בלעם הרשע tovah klalah
shekilel Achiyah HaShiloni et Yisrael yoter mivracha shebercham Bilam HaRasha
I’d rather be beaten up by my friends than kissed by my
enemies is basically what it’s saying. Better is the curse that אחיה
השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni the prophet cursed ישראל Yisrael better than the blessings
that בלעם Bilam has given us. Why? אחיה השילוני קילל את ישראל
בקנה Achiyah HaShiloni kilel et Yisrael bakaneh When he wanted to curse
us, he used the imagery of a reed, שנאמר it says, והכה
ה׳ את ישראל כאשר ינוד הקנה במים vehika Hashem et Yisrael kaasher
yanud hakaneh bamayim God will smite ישראל Yisrael?
like the reed will sort of sway in the waters. Okay, so
what seems like a very bad image, right? We won’t be firm,
we’ll be swaying. But no, it’s actually at the root of it
is a very good image. מה קנה זה עומד במקום מים ma
kaneh zeh omed bimkom mayim
So if you know you think about a reed in water, no
matter how many waters pass by, the reed stays where it’s planted.
The waters in the end don’t uproot it. Bad things happen to
it but it doesn’t get destroyed. וגזעו מחליף vegizo machalif even if
it’s cut down it grows back. ושרשיו מרובים vasharashav merubim and has
very deep roots.
ואפילו כל רוחות שבעולם באות ונושבות בו אין מזיזות אותו ממקומו vaafilu
kol ruchot shebaolam baot venoshvot bo ein mezizot oto mimkomo
because of its flexibility, they don’t uproot it from its place, אלא
הוא הולך ובא עמהם ela hu holech uva imahem
but it like sways with the wind, rolls with the punches. כיון
שדמו הרוחות keivan shedamu haruchot
and when the winds finally cease, עמד הקנה במקומו amad hakaneh bimkomo
it’s where it always was. So it’s able to withstand no matter
how much you know sort of anguish and travails and so on.
So that curse is really a blessing. We’ll suffer but we’ll be
able to withstand it all. אבל בלעם הרשע aval Bilam HaRasha the
wicked בלעם Bilam בירכם בארז bercham beerez When he blessed us, he
compared us to a cedar tree, כארזים עלי מים יפרח כארז בלבנון
ישגה kaarezim alei mayim yifrach kaerez baLevanon yisgeh What can I tell
you? Alright, that doesn’t fit our point right now. מה ארז זה
אינו עומד במקום מים ma erez zeh eino omed bimkom mayim An
ארז erez does not grow out of the water. Okay, an ארז
erez grows I guess in a forest, not by the water. Maybe
presumably also water is the imagery of תורה Torah source of life.
ושרשיו מועטים vasharashav muatim and has shallow roots, ואין גזעו מחליף veein
gizo machalif if it’s cut down it doesn’t grow back. אפילו כל
רוחות שבעולם באות ונושבות בו אין מזיזות אותו ממקומו afilu kol ruchot
shebaolam baot venoshvot bo ein mezizot oto mimkomo It’s true that because
of its sturdiness, normal wind doesn’t get it to move, right? It’ll
just stay firm, it won’t even bend with the wind. But כיון
שנשבה רוח דרומית keivan shenashva ruach dromit if a very powerful wind,
if like a hurricane hits it, okay,
מיד עוקרתו והופכתו על פניו miyad okarto vehofachto al panav and it’ll
knock it down and upturn it. ולא עוד אלא velo od ela
okay so therefore so even within that blessing ultimately is a hidden
curse, and within the curse is a hidden blessing, okay, what that
we got the curse that we got from אחיה השילוני Achiyah HaShiloni
ולא עוד velo od not only that, the imagery of it of
the reed is good in another way. אלא שזכה קנה ליטול הימנו
קולמוס לכתוב ממנו ספר תורה ela shezacha kaneh litol himenu kulmus lichtov
mimenu Sefer Torah but the reed gets used to be made a
you know a quill to write a ספר תורה Sefer Torah So
ultimately yes bad things will happen, but ultimately it speaks about it
you know about its sort of more spiritual orientation and the fact
that it’s able to withstand those things. Okay.
נביאים וכתובים Nevi'im uKetuvim ספר תורה Sefer Torah and okay fine. What’s
the one intention? One is to uphold the people by rebuking them
and the other is to try and destroy them. Ah, right. I
mean well the blessing right the blessing was rooted in an attempt
to destroy. That is correct whereas אחיה Achiyah is trying to ultimately
do good. That is absolutely correct, that’s well said.
Yeah, you’re right and you know that fits also the verse, right?
Because when a friend like says wounds you, you know, maybe says
harsh words, critical words or whatever, it’s ultimately coming out of friendship,
whereas when an enemy does nice things to you, it’s usually coming
out of some ulterior motive, you know, and some hidden agenda. That’s
a very good point.
Okay, וירא את הקיני vayar et haKeini Now back to בלעם Bilam.
He saw the קיני Keini וישא משלו ויאמר vayisa meshalo vayomar and
he lifted up his parable and he said, right,
איתן מושבך ושים בסלע קינך eitan moshavcha vesim basela kinecha the end
of the pasuk, strong is your dwelling place and you place in
the rock your nest. קיני Keini and קינך kinecha obviously a little
play on words. אמר לו בלעם ליתרו amar lo Bilam leYitro קיני
Keini here is יתרו Yitro okay. He said to יתרו Yitro קיני
Kini קיני Kini
like not קיני Keini not Canaanite קיני Keini לא היית עמנו באותה
עצה lo hayita imanu beotah eitzah I don’t get it. How did
you merit to such greatness? Weren’t you with us with that whole
you know in that whole meeting there with פרעה Paroh according to
the מדרש Midrash which we’re about to see, when פרעה Paroh took
advice what to do with the Israelites, there were three people there,
בלעם Bilam יתרו Yitro and איוב Iyov So you were part of
that whole plot. So this is rhetorical. Weren't you there with us?
And so מה הושיבך איתן עולם, ma hoshivcha eitan olam, so איתן
מושבך, eitan moshavcha, strong is your dwelling place, who allowed you to
dwell with the strong ones, the mighty ones of the world, who
allowed you to dwell with ישראל? Yisrael. You were part of you
were part of the plot. והיינו דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא רבי
סימאי, ve'hainu d'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba Rabbi Simai, and this is
based on the whole דרשה, drasha, on the whole מדרש, Midrash, שלושה
היו באותה עצה, shlosha hayu b'ota eitza, there were three in that
plot to destroy the Israelites. אלו הם בלעם, איוב, ויתרו, elu hem
Bilam, Iyov, ve'Yitro, בלעם, איוב, ויתרו. Bilam, Iyov, ve'Yitro.
So בלעם שיעץ, Bilam she'ya'atz,
בלעם Bilam's gave the advice to throw the babies in the Nile,
like so we see later, right, that בלעם Bilam's gives advice to
בלק Balak that ultimately leads to the downfall of the people at
whatever, at least the way חז"ל Chazal connects the connects the dots.
So he was the one who gave the advice.
So בלעם שיעץ נהרג, Bilam she'ya'atz neherag, he was killed, right, which
comes later in the תורה Torah which we're going to get to
at the bottom of the דף. daf. איוב ששתק, Iyov she'shatak, איוב,
Iyov, you know, wasn't in favor, but he didn't have the courage
to speak up against פרעה, Paroh, so he was silent. So נידון
בייסורין, nidon b'yisurin, so he suffered, you know, that's the explanation for
all the sufferings of איוב, Iyov, right, which is
important. Right,
it's not just about did you do evil or not, but even
like not standing up against evil, silence. And of course, you know,
part of this also plays off the beginning story about איוב Iyov
where the bad things initially happen to him and he remains silent,
right, you know, if you remember the story when the first bad
things happen to him he said like he did not speak up
against God, he did not speak up against God, and then finally
worse and worse things and then he said something. So it's sort
of playing on this theme that when like he doesn't speak up,
you know. So anyway, so he suffered. יתרו שברח, Yitro she'barach, and
יתרו, Yitro, he was not, you know, he couldn't speak up, maybe
it wouldn't have done any good, he would have been killed, but
he wasn't going to be a like just a silent bystander, so
he ran away like to at least separate himself from everything that
was going on. So, and because of that, he left the evil
פרעה, Paroh, so then he was brought taken in eventually by ישראל.
זכו בני בניו לישב בלשכת הגזית, zachu b'nei banav layshev b'Lishkat HaGazit,
his descendants dwell in the chamber of the hewn stone where the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin is in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. This is, we
just had this just a just a few days ago, okay? And
that's איתן מושבך, eitan moshavcha, that's why you dwell amongst the mighty
ones, because you were, yes, you were taken in, you were in
the meeting, but then you rejected it and you ran away.
שנאמר ומשפחות סופרים יושבי יעבץ, shene'emar umishpachot sofrim yoshvei Yabetz, as it's
said, the family of scribes, יושבי יעבץ, yoshvei Yabetz, יעבץ Yabetz here's
read as to mean the same to the לשכת הגזית. Lishkat HaGazit.
תרעתים שמעתים שוכתים, Tir'atim Shim'atim Suchatim, so that's the name of the
family. המה הקינים הבאים מחמת אבי בית רכב, hema ha'Kinim haba'im me'Chamat
avi beit Rechav, those are the קינים Kinim who came from חמת,
Chamat, the father of בית רכב. Beit Rechav. וכי המה הקינים, vechi
hema ha'Kinim, and who are the קינים? Kinim? וכתיב ובני קיני חותן
משה, u'chtiv u'vnei Keini choten Moshe, the sons of קיני, Keini, the
father-in-law of משה, Moshe, עלו מעיר התמרים, alu me'ir hatmarim, etc. So
what does that prove? That's that קיני Keini is the is the
משפחת סופרים, mishpachat sofrim, and יושבי יעבץ yoshvei Yabetz means that they
dwell in the לשכת הגזית. Lishkat HaGazit. I don't know exactly how
יעבץ Yabetz is לשכת הגזית. Lishkat HaGazit. Okay. It's an interesting metaphor
of יתרו Yitro running away. I think it sort of to me
seems like running away from your problems kind of thing instead of
dealing with it. Well, משה Moshe also runs away when he's about
to get caught by פרעה. Paroh. He's not he's not he's not
being complicit. So you can, you know, you can speak up,
if you're silent and remain in place then you're complicit. So you
can speak up and get killed, you can run away, but there
are a limited number of things that you can do when you
know when you've got a tyrant there. Okay.
Okay, וישא משלו ויאמר אוי מי יחיה משומו אל. vayi'sa mishalo vayomar
oy mi yichye mi'shumo El. He lifted up his parable and he
said, woe, who would live when God does these things? So what
does that mean? ואמר רבי שמעון בן לוי, v'amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Levi, אוי מי שמחיה עצמו בשם אל. oy mi she'mechayeh atzmo b'shem
El. So from the word משומו, mishumo, משמו, mi'shmo, the name of
God, woe is the person who gives himself life from the name
of God. What does that mean? That sounds like a good thing,
like you learn תורה Torah gives you life. Anyway, but רש"י Rashi
says a couple of explanations, but the first and probably the פשט
pshat is a person who makes himself into a god, who treats
himself as a god. Now רש"י Rashi has two explanations, one is
literally, goes around and says that he's a god. And the other,
which then probably and maybe one of the reasons it's taken out,
is some scholars think
that it's obviously a not so shielded critique of Jesus and Christianity.
Or the other explanation רש"י Rashi says is a person that goes
ahead and decides, you know, that they're going to just like, like
act as a god on this earth, meaning just like live a
godless life and just, you know, enjoy the sensory plea, you know,
sensual pleasures and so on. Okay, but it probably means more of
the former. Oh, but it doesn't mean someone using God's name for
an incantation? It could be, but that's not the way רש"י Rashi
reads it. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan.
here's another one, אוי לה לאומה שתמצא בשעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא עושה
פדיון לבניו. oy lah l'uma she'timatze b'sha'a she'HaKadosh Baruch Hu oseh pidyon
l'vanav. So this is probably more closer to the פשט, pshat, woe
is the one who will be there when God does these things.
What are these things? Woe is the nation that tries to sort
of get in the way when God comes to redeem His people.
The ones who are in the way. לשים, L'sim, when God does
these things, places these things, creates, effects these things. אוי לה לאומה
שתמצא בשעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא עושה פדיון לבניו. Oy la l'uma shetimatzei
b'sha'ah sheHaKadosh Baruch Hu oseh pidyon l'vanav. מי מטיל כסותו, Mi matil
ksuto, who's the ones that thinks that you can put your garment
בין לביא ללביאה בשעה שנזקקין זה עם זה bein lavi l'lviyah b'sha'ah
she'niska'akin zeh im zeh between a lion and a lioness when they
are having, when they are copulating?
It is a very interesting metaphor. Right. I mean, they're both these
powerful things. I mean, most of the time, they're very quiet. Right?
I mean, lions, most of the time they look like they're lazy.
Right? I mean, ever go to the zoo? They're just hanging around
doing nothing. But when they actually are acting, their power comes forth.
Right. But the idea of that sort of the male and the
female, right, it's not that we're God's children or God's whatever, it's
like this whole the male-female copulating, whatever is, I mean, the Kabbalists
love it. But anyway. All right. So, okay, וצים מיד כתים, v'tzim
miyad Kittim, now וצים tzim from the hands of כתים. Kittim. So
אמר רב ליבון אספיר. Amar Rav Libun Aspir. So, I don't know,
there's I read the what's-his-name, Soncino, they have some fascinating explanations. It's
like some of the white kingdom or I don't know. Anyway, some
fascinating discussions about what this might be referring to. But he does
suggest the region of,
yeah, the white legion. But what do they say that means historically?
Do they have anything? They don't know if it's the Byzantine region
or the region of souls. What is אספיר? Aspir? אספיר Aspir is
a word for legion of soldiers. Right? Yeah, but here I'll read
you
what Soncino says. Soncino usually has the more interesting, what do you
call it, historical things. Here, he says like
this: ליבון אספיר... Libun Aspir... okay, so some read אספר Aspar as
the Persian אסואר Aswar which means knight, a legion of knights, some
want to say. The sources accordingly interprets legions will come from the
coast of כתים, Kittim, כתים Kittim being taken to denote Rome. Jastrow
reads the whole passage as an interpolation of eighth or ninth century
and referring to Leo the Isaurian, the Byzantine emperor, leader of the
iconoclastic movement which caused a long war between the East and West
of the empire. So that I guess would be the ליבון. Libun.
All right, whatever. You see
here, yes, histor along those lines, legion, you know, ליבון, Libun, ליגיון,
Legion, you know, that's it. And then אספיר, Aspir, some
Greek derivation, tactical unit. Okay, there you go. Okay, וענו אשור וענו
עבר, v'inu Ashur v'inu Ever, and they will afflict Assyria and they
will afflict Ever. עד אשור קטלי מיקטל, Ad asher katli miktal, I
don't get how they're getting this next thing from the verse because
it's the same word, but up to Ashur they will
they will kill people. מכאן ואילך משעבדי שעבודי, Mikan v'eilach m'shabdi shibudei,
they will no longer be killing people, they'll be subjugating them. All
right. הנני הולך לעמי. Humni oileich l'ami. Now then Bilam says to
Balak, I'm going back to my people. לכה איעצך אשר יעשה העם
הזה לעמך באחרית הימים, L'cha i'atzcha asher ya'aseh ha'am hazeh l'amcha b'acharit
hayamim, let me go tell you what this nation will do to
your nation in the end of days. Okay, so fine, like what's
going to happen to the nation of Moab through the hands of
בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. But according to the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא
Gemara understands that this is where he gave him advice to have
the Moabite and Midianite women or whatever seduce בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
The reason it does it is because later it says,
הן הנה היו לבני ישראל על דבר בלעם, hein heinah hayu l'vnei
Yisrael al dvar Bilam, they were against בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael through
the
advice, through the word of Bilam. So it understands that Bilam was
the one who gave Balak this advice and it connects it to
this verse. But this verse says, let me tell you what this
people is going to do to your people. But according to the
way the גמרא Gemara wants to connect the dots, it says I
want to give you advice how what you should do to them.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara just asks. The גמרא Gemara says,
אשר יעשה העם הזה לעמך באחרית, Asher ya'aseh ha'am hazeh l'amcha b'acharit,
עמך לעם הזה מיבעי ליה. Amcha l'am hazeh miba'ei lei. It should
be what your nation should do to this nation, not what this
nation will do to your nation, because he's going to give them
advice how to, you know, how to cause the downfall of בני
ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So, אמר רבי אבא בר כהנא, אדם שמקלל עצמו
ותולה קללתו באחרים. adam shem'kalel etzmo v'tola klilato b'acherim.
Right, he just wanted to reverse it, like when we say שונאיהם
של ישראל. soneihem shel Yisrael. Now why does he want to reverse
it? Right? I mean, he wants to speak to Balak, he wants
to speak about the downfall of בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So, wait,
wait. So Rashi has two explanations, but the second one, which is
the easier one, is no, Balak said it the normal way, Bilam
said it the normal way, let me tell you how you should
cause the downfall of this people, what you should do to them.
But when the פסוק pasuk. wrote it, it wrote it in the
reverse. It, you know, so it didn't want to sort of... okay,
so anyway, it's a type of euphemism. But basically we're reading this
as the advice Bilam gives Balak to cause בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
to sin. Okay, so where were we? אמר להם אלהיהם של אלו
שונא זמה הוא, Amar lahem eloheihem shel eilu sonei zimah hu, this
the God of this people hates sexual fornication. והם מתאוים לכלי פשתן,
v'heim mitavin l'chlei pishtan, and by the way, this is completely bizarre,
they happen to like nice linen clothes. Okay, why is that relevant?
Okay, בא ואעצך עצה. Bo v'i'atzcha eitzah. Because by... be the downfall
of many. Exactly. That's what I was thinking. You know those linen
garments have led so many people astray. So let me give you
some advice. עשה להן קלעים, Asei lahen kla'im, go hang out some
curtains. Now it doesn't seem that these curtains are necessarily the linen
garments. It's sort of like a street fair it sounds the way
it's described. Okay, go you know put these tents up, make a
street fair והושיב בהן זונות Vehoshiv bahen zonot and have some prostitutes
be manning the booths in these street fairs. זקינה מבחוץ וילדה מבפנים,
Zkeinah mibachutz veyaldah mibifnim, have the older one on the outside
so
it won't be obvious that they're being tried to be seduced and
you know the younger more attractive more seductive one on the inside.
וימכרו להן כלי פשתן Veyimkru lahen klei pishtan and these booths will
be selling you know linen garments which will get them to come
and take a
look. עשה להן קלעים Asei lahen kla'im so עשה להן קלעים Asei
lahen kla'im make make for them these you know he did it
עשה להן קלעים Asei lahen kla'im so then he did. Oh right
right guys thank you sorry that was the first time. עשה להן
קלעים Asei lahen kla'im so he made these curtains מהר שלג עד
בית הישימות Mehar sheleg ad beit hayeshimot from from the Mount Sheleg
to Beit Hayeshimot he created this like huge street fair or whatever
you know a wilderness fair והושיב בהן זונות Vehoshiv bahen zonot and
he followed the advice he put the prostitutes there זקינה מבחוץ וילדה
מבפנים Zkeinah mibachutz veyaldah mibifnim the older one on the outside the
younger one on the inside ובשעה שישראל אוכלין ושותין ושמחים Uvesha'ah sheYisrael
ochlin veshotin vesmeichim and while Israel were eating and drinking and being
happy ויוצאים לטייל בשוק Veyotzim letayel bashuk and you know you have
to imagine that they are projecting from a reality that they experienced
you know I guess in the Roman marketplaces or whatever you know
but so I do wonder though how much like were there prostitutes
I mean actually that comes up in other places right where there's
at the beginning of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah it says Oh the
Romans are you know they really did so wonderful things they made
these you know you know whatever they made the fairs and they
made these markets and they made the bathhouses and no the only
only the markets to make booths for the prostitutes to be in.
So it definitely seemed like in these markets these Roman markets there
were these you know the prostitutes were doing some a brisk business.
So they're sort of retroprojecting this whole experience. Okay. So and he
did this.
ובשעה שישראל אוכלין ושותין ושמחים Uvesha'ah sheYisrael ochlin veshotin vesmeichim and they
were enjoying the good food of the street fair ויוצאים לטייל בשוק
Veyotzim letayel bashuk and they were going and walking in the market.
אומרת לו זקינה התבקש כלי פשתן Omeret lo zkeinah hitvakesh klei pishtan
so the older woman says Hey aren't you aren't you wouldn't you
be interested in some nice beautiful linen garments? Okay. זקינה אומרת לו
בשווה Zkeinah omeret lo beshaveh
now
he says Yeah how much is it? So the older woman gives
him like the fair market price and he's haggling there. וילדה אומרת
לו בפחות Veyaldah omeret lo befachot and then the younger attractive woman
she's saying Oh no come I'll give you 20% discount. Oh so
he follows the younger one gets you know that's another way to
get us by giving us a discount. שתים ושלש פעמים Shtayim veshalosh
pe'amim
so
this happens two or three times so they're spending a lot of
time with these younger women and it's all in the context of
like trying to get a good deal on these linen garments okay.
The irony also is that you imagine although it's not saying it
like I don't know I'm imagining who likes you know presumably the
I think the cultural assumption would be it would be the women
who would you know want the linen garment. So there are these
men they're trying to buy some nice you know material for their
wives while they're being I don't know if that's exactly a subtext.
I'm just reading that in. But anyway. Okay so spends you know
tells it two or three times. ואחר כך אומרת לו הרי אתה
כבן בית Ve'achar kach omeret lo harei atah keven bayit you know
what you've been spending so much time here you know as we've
been discussing price you've come back to buy from me a few
times.
שב גו רולי לעצמך Shev go rolei le'atzmecha you know you can
look search through the wares on your own spend come here you
know spend a little time. וצלוחית של יין עמוני מונח אצלה Utzlochit
shel yayin Amoni munach etzlah
and she had a little flask of Ammonite wine. It's funny they're
Moab why it's mentioning Ammon wine? I don't know. Anyway. ועדיין לא
נאסר יין של נכרים Ve'adayin lo ne'esar yayin shel nochrim here's a
little interpolation Oh by the way at that stage since it was
in the biblical and not yet the rabbinic period ועדיין לא נאסר
יין של נכרים Ve'adayin lo ne'esar yayin shel nochrim
the wine of non-Jews had not yet been forbidden. That didn't mention
why they were אוכלין ושותין ochlin veshotin I guess they assume it
was vegetarian fair or something. Okay and they were able to drink
wine also because and also giving a hint about why the wine
should be forbidden you know because you know you're able to when
you when you socialize with wine one thing leads to another. אמר
לה Amar lah so he's he spent some time he was drinking
wine. רצונך שתשתה כוס של יין Retzoncha shetishteh kos shel yayin
so would you like some wine? Of course. כיון ששתה בער בו
Keivan sheshatah ba'ar bo he drank the wine. בער בו Ba'ar bo
so his you know his lust was was was inflamed thank you.
אמר לה השמיעי לי Amar lah hashmi'i li and then he said
to her listen to me have sex with me. הוציאה יראתה מתוך
חיקה Hotzi'ah yiratah mitoch cheikah now she used this as leverage. She
took out her her idol from her from her bosom. אמר לה
Amar lah she said to him. עבוד לזה. avod lazeh.
First worship my god and then I'll agree to you. אמר לה,
Amar lah, he said to her, הלא יהודי אני. halo Yehudi ani.
Talk about a retro-rejection, right? I'm a Jew, like and הלא ישראלי
אני, halo Yisraeli ani, it's הלא יהודי אני. halo Yehudi ani. I'm
a Jew. אמר לו, Amar lo, what, so obviously it's also a
way of course that the rabbis are critiquing or alerting people to
the dangers, you know, about like now we alert people to the
dangers of the internet, right? They were alerting them like you know
all of these you know what is it called like you know
whatever all of these of things are available to them. You have
to be you have to be aware how these different things could
seduce you when you when you when you allow yourself this you
know this emporia of options and of you know and of pleasures
as it were. So anyway, he said to her, I am a
Jew, I'm a Jew. אמר לו ומה איכפת לך? Amar lo u'ma
ichpat lach? All right, big deal you're a Jew. קום ומבקש ממך
עיפור. Kum u'vakesh mimcha iypur. I'm not asking from you anything that
would really compromise your religion. Just go ahead and defecate in front
of it. And you know, that's obviously not a serious problem. והוא
אינו יודע שעבודתו בכך. V'hu eino yodea she'avodato be'kach. That's the problem.
Is he going to be held liable for doing that? Well, but
the point is he knows that there's a problem. I mean, whatever,
first of all as you see that's inserted into the text. No,
but I'm saying based on what we learned. Yeah, but the question
is not making him חייב chayav for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The
question is how one thing led to the next, as we'll see.
You know, you get people to step over little lines, right? That's
the way. Every, you know, a little line, a little line, a
little line and then somebody goes much, you know, further than they
ever would have imagined going. All right, so תרעב עוד אלא שאיני
מניחתך עד שתכפור בתורת משה רבך. t'rov od ela she'eini menachtech ad
shetichpor b'torat Moshe rabbach.
Now that of course doesn't follow, right? It seems like he was
on his guard and then she says, oh, all I'm asking you
to do is just defecate, oh and also deny your faith. You
know, deny your Torah. So רש"י Rashi inserts after he did this,
then she said, ah, you know, one thing led to the next
and he got she got him to tiny little things each one
which she sort of minimized the problem to the point where it's
like basically he had taken so many steps away from, you know,
where he normally you know where his line was that she said
now if you really want want, you know, want to have sex
with me you have to deny the Torah of of Moshe. שנאמר
המה באו בעל פעור, Shene'emar heima ba'u ba'al pe'or,
they went to the בעל פעור, ba'al pe'or, וינזרו לבשת vayinazru laboshet
and they strayed for their embarrassment. ויהיו שקוצים באהבם Vehayu shikutzim be'ahavam
and they became like sort of abominations with their love or or
lust here. Okay, so basically because of the enticements of, you know,
this whole this whole world here it ultimately, you know, they were
led astray.
וישב
ישראל בשיטים, Vayeshev Yisrael bashitim, Israel dwelt in
the
שיטים. Shitim. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, שיטים שמו, shitim shemo,
that was its name. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, so there's
going to be a consistent debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua interprets these things midrashically,
or you know sort of like as there's meaning in the names.
רבי יהושע אומר שנתעסקו בדברי שטות. Rabbi Yehoshua omer she'nitasku b'divrei shtut.
No, they were led astray by nonsense. ותקראן לעם לזבחי אלוהיהן, Vatikrena
la'am l'zivchei eloheihen, they called the people to worship to their gods,
to sacrifice to their gods. רבי אליעזר אומר ערומות פגעו בהן. Rabbi
Eliezer omer arumot pagu bahen. They they came up to them naked
and sort of, you know, so it's a very blatant type of
a seduction.
I don't know where he gets that from the פסוק. pasuk רבי
יהושע אומר שנתן בכולם בעל קרי. Rabbi Yehoshua omer shenatan b'kulam ba'al
keri. Well that's the whole point of a שיטה? shita? Well
that's a different version. Okay, that they all became ותקראן Vatikrena for
בעל קרי, ba'al keri, all the people sort of became, you know,
had seminal emission. מה רשע רפידים? Ma rasha refidim? Now, because we're
mentioning one debate of רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua we
mention another one about a meaning of a name, by the רפידים
Refidim and by עמלק. Amalek. רבי אליעזר אומר רפידים שמו, Rabbi Eliezer
omer Refidim shemo, that was just the name where עמלק Amalek encountered
them. רבי יהושע אומר שריפו עצמן מדברי תורה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer sherifu
atzman midivrei Torah. No, their hands were weakened from Torah, the word
רפיון riphayon from רפידים Refidim and that led to עמלק Amalek to
attack. שנאמר לא הפנו אבות אל בנים מרפיון ידים. Shene'emar lo hifnu
avot el banim merifyon yadayim. The fathers did not turn to the
sons from the weakness of the hands, so the word רפיון. riphayon.
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan, and
then what?
ויחל העם לזנות בבנות מואב, Vayachel ha'am liznot b'vnot Moav, they began
to fornicate.
וישב, Vayeshev, don't we have
בטח בדד עין יעקב? betach badad ein Yaakov?
That's a point. Okay, that's not historical, though, that's a ברכה, beracha.
but that's a good question. You know, you're always bringing
counterexamples, not helpful. וישב יעקב בארץ מגורי אביו, Vayeshev Yaakov b'eretz megurei
aviv, of course, that's exactly right what Rabbi Yochanan right after Reish
Lakish passed away, whoever it was, every time he said something, somebody
said, oh, here's a proof, here's a proof, and he said, what
do I need you for? When Reish Lakish was alive, every time
I said something, he brought me ten counterexamples. Okay, but it's not
helpful when trying to get to a big דף. All right, anyway,
all right,
ונאמר, v'ne'emar, let's see, what, וישב יעקב בארץ מגורי אביו, Vayeshev Yaakov
b'eretz megurei aviv, he dwelt in the land of his forefathers, בארץ
כנען, b'eretz Canaan, and then ויבא יוסף את דבתם רעה אל אביהם,
vayavei Yosef et dibatam ra'ah el avihem, what happens? It's the whole
bringing of the evil speech and going down into the exile and
selling of Yosef. ונאמר וישב ישראל בארץ גושן, v'ne'emar vayeshev Yisrael b'eretz
Goshen, they dwelt in the land of Goshen, and ויקרבו ימי ישראל
למות, v'yikrevu yemei Yisrael lamut, his time came to die. Well, that's
another, that's a pretty weak one because, you know, it sounds like
they had it good in the land of Goshen, and people do
die eventually. It wasn't like some tragedy ensued, right? He just died,
his time came, he lived to a nice old age.
Anyway, okay. וישב יהודה וישראל לבטח איש תחת
גפנו ותחת תאנתו, Vayeshev Yehuda v'Yisrael lavetach ish tachat gafno v'tachat te'enato,
they dwelt in security, man under his vine and under his fig
tree. That also sounds good. And then if you go about
seven chapters later, ויקם ה' שטן לשלמה את הדד האדומי מזרע המלך
הוא באדום, vayakam Hashem satan l'Shlomo et Hadad ha'Adomi mizerah hamelech hu
v'Edom,
and that this king of this Edomite rose up against Shlomo and
did war against Shlomo. So it's a bit of a stretch already,
Michael, even going before your verses, right? I mean, you have to
go seven chapters later to get something bad happening. Okay,
anyway, sort of like ויהי לשון צער. vayehi lashon tza'ar. Yeah, exactly.
ואת מלכי מדין הרגו על חלליהם, V'et malchei Midyan hargu al chalaleihem,
back to the story. So they killed the kings of Midian when
they went out to war against the Midianites. And then it says,
ואת בלעם בן בעור הרגו בחרב, v'et Bilam ben Be'or hargu bacharev,
they killed Bilam. So what was Bilam doing against the Midianites? He
left the king of Moav, he went back to his people. Where,
how did he get caught up in this war against the Midian?
Okay, but remember, the war against the Midian is also not exactly
clear the role the Midianites played, right? Because it says that they
fornicated after בנות מואב, bnot Moav, but then the story with Pinchas
was, right, as whatever it was, ויקרב אל אחיו את המדינית, v'yakrev
el achav et haMidyanit, זמרי, Zimri, right? And somehow it's the Midianites
that get focused on as the primary perpetrators even though the context
was all about Moav and the opening verse was Moav. So they
went to war against the Midianites and somehow Bilam happens to be
there. And we just said that Bilam was the one who gave
them the advice. Okay, so Bilam מה בעי התם, mah ba'ei hatam,
what was he doing back in Midian? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan שהלך ליטול שכר עשרים וארבעה אלף שנפלו מישראל, shehalach litol schar
esrim v'arba'ah elef she'naflu mi'Yisrael, because his advice led to twenty a
plague, 24,000 died, he wanted to get his payment for his good
advice.
And as a result, he got killed. אמר מר זוטרא בר טוביה
אמר רב, Amar Mar Zutra bar Tuvia amar Rav, היינו דאמרי אינשי,
hainu d'amri inshi, that's what people say: גמלא אזלא למיבעי קרני, gamla
azla lemib'ei karnei, a camel goes to ask for a horn, it's
not happy enough with its hump or whatever, it wants a horn,
so אודני דהוו ליה גזיזי מיניה, udnei d'havu lei gezizi minei,
so as a result, it gets its ears cut off. You know,
don't go ahead and be asking for a little, be a little
too greedy and asking for too much. I was just listening the
other night to a the other day to a podcast called It's
Undiscovered.
It's a nice podcast, it's about like the backstories of science, like
you know the people's and the history or whatever. Anyway, so it
was about this question about like you know about trying to control
the weather and seeding clouds and how that started or whatever. Anyway,
but it tells the story about a guy who was like he
had a pretty good reputation about being able to get things to
rain, you know, get it to rain. So he was hired by
San by the city of San Diego, like they were offered ten
thousand dollars, this was like I think at the end of the
19th or the beginning of the 20th century, maybe. Anyway, if he
could like fill up their you know the rivers or whatever it
would be they would give him ten thousand dollars. So he did
whatever he did, you know, threw some chemicals into the air. Anyway,
pretty soon after it started raining and raining and pouring and pouring
and pouring and pouring many days and it flooded and it did
like ten million dollars worth of damage. So anyway, he it's sort
of like a חוני המעגל Choni HaMa'agal story. So you know, so
because sometimes, you know, things happen by coincidence and you assume causal
relationships. Anyway, he ran away. A year later he came back and
he wanted to get paid.
And they said to him, you want to get paid? Here's the
ten million dollars bill for the damages you caused. If you want
to take credit for it, then you're going to take that, you
know, then you have to take credit. Okay, so anyway, so he
wanted so this Bilam went back to get paid and this is
what happened to him. אמר מר זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב, Amar
Mar Zutra bar Tuvia amar Rav, היינו דאמרי אינשי, hainu d'amri inshi,
what we just said. Okay. ואת בלעם בן בעור הקוסם, V'et Bilam
ben Be'or hakosem, this is in יהושע, Yehoshua, Bilam ben Be'or the
magician or whatever.
קוסם, Kosem, magician or whatever? נביא, Navi, he's a prophet, right? I
mean when יהושע Yehoshua's retelling it, it's not surprising that יהושע Yehoshua
wants to downplay his weight. You don't want to call him a
נביא. navi. But okay, but how do you reconcile that? אמר רבי
יוחנן בתחילה נביא ולבסוף קוסם. Amar Rabbi Yochanan bitechilah navi ulevasof kosem.
Yeah, he started as a נביא, navi, but in the end, right,
he had, you know,
when he wasn't getting God to do it, he was trying these
more magical devices, you know, maybe. What does רש"י Rashi say? שנתן
עיניו במלכות וניטלה הימנו נבואה. Shenatan einav bemalchut venittela heimenu nevuah. Oh
no, רש"י Rashi says that God as a result, because he tried
to do this bad thing, God removed the ability of prophecy from
him. אמר
רבי יוחנן היינו דאמרי אינשי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan haynu d'amrei inshi, that's
what people say,
מסגני ושלטי הוי, misagnei v'shalti havai, this woman came from kings and
leaders,
איזין לגבי נגרי, izin legabi nagrei, she winds up being a prostitute
for carpenters. Okay, so it's like the mighty have fallen. All
right.
הרגו בני ישראל בחרב, Hargu benei Yisrael becherev, back to the פסוק
pasuk in יהושע, Yehoshua, so the בני ישראל benei Yisrael killed him
with a sword, this בלעם. Bilam So אל חלליהם, el chalaleihem, on
their corpses. So the extra אל חלליהם el chalaleihem is like a
little superfluous and we're reading it's going to mean like multiple deaths
they inflicted upon him. אמר רב שקיימו בו ארבע מיתות סקילה שרפה
הרג וחנק. Amar Rav shekiyemu bo arba mitot sekilah sreifah hereg vechenek.
So they did all the things. So רש"י Rashi says how'd they
get that? I don't know, the extra word I think of אל
חלליהם. el chalaleihem. So the חלליהם chalaleihem is like a multiplicity. What
does it mean they killed him on on the corpses? Okay, so
it's like they made him into a corpse multiple times. Okay, they
hanged him, they burnt him on the on the cross or on
the whenever on the thing he was hanging on, then they chopped
off his head and then that was I don't know, whatever. Okay.
אמר ליה ההוא מינא לרבי חנינא. Amar lei hahu mina leRabbi Chanina.
So a certain apostate or sectarian said to רבי חנינא: Rabbi Chanina:
מי שמיע
לך בלעם בר כמה הוי? Mi shemia lach Bilam bar kamah havai?
Now this doesn't seem like doesn't seem like a classic, you know,
מין min trying to make trouble. He says, "Hey, you know how
old בלעם Bilam was when he died?" אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said to him, מכתב לא כתיב, michtav lo ketiv, it's not written.
אלא מדכתיב אנשי דמים ומרמה לא יחצו ימיהם, Ela midechetiv anshei damim
umirmah lo yechetzu yemeihem, the people of, you know, of blood and
of deceit, they will not live to half their lives, so either
בר תלתין ותלת שנין או בר תלתין וארבע, bar tlatin utlat shanin
o bar tlatin ve'arba, either thirty-three or thirty-four. So whenever it says
מין min like there's a good chance he's talking about a Hebrew,
like a like a Jewish Christian,
and Jesus was in his thirties, right? About thirty-three. He was about
thirty-three, thirty-four. Yeah, so that's what I was thinking that this was
a hidden reference to Jesus. אמר ליה שפיר קאמרת. Amar lei shappir
ka'amrat. You know what? That's good, good answer. You passed the test.
לדידי חזי לי פנקסיה דבלעם, Ledidi chazi li pinkasei deBilam, I actually
happened to see בלעם's Bilam's diary. Man, that's what that would get
you on eBay. I happened to see בלעם's Bilam diary and it
was written in it: בר תלתין ותלת שנין בלעם חגירא, Bar tlatin
utlat shanin Bilam chagira, thirty-three years old was בלעם Bilam's the lame
person. Remember before we said he was lame? קטליה פנחס ליסטאה, Katilei
Pinchas Lista'ah, so I don't know how בלעם Bilam's was writing this,
maybe his sons wrote this in his diary, like last eight פסוקים
pesukim in the תורה, Torah, right? Which speaks about משה's Moshe's death.
Anyway, somehow in בלעם's Bilam? diary or ledger was written that בלעם
Bilam, the lame person was thirty-three when פנחס Pinchas smote him, ליסטאה.
lista'ah. Now ליסטאה, lista'ah, רש"י Rashi here interprets to mean like like
a sergeant, an officer, but ליסטאה lista'ah usually means like a a
bandit. So this is remember, this is from בלעם's Bilam perspective or
the perspective of whoever's writing in בלעם's diary. So it makes פנחס
Pinchas into the, you know, into the wicked one. Now the question
is where did פנחס Pinchas kill בלעם? So רש"י Rashi says well,
he didn't personally have to kill him, but he was the one
leading the war effort, so it's like he killed him.
Okay. אמר ליה מר בריה דרבינא לבריה. Amar lei Mar brei deRavina
levrei. So מר Mar the son of רבינא Ravina said to his
son, בכולהו לא תפיש למדרש, bekulhu lo tapish limidrash, and
remember we had the issue before about spending too much time talking
about the evil of the kings and about how the kings were,
you know, the Jewish kings were great people, etc. So he says,
look, when you spend time like, you know, learning פרק חלק and
talking about all the evil of the people that don't have a
חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba, you know, don't do too much
about everybody about about the Jews there, like about the kings and
the commoners, like, you know, say the bad stuff but don't go
don't spend a lot of time on it, לבר מבלעם הרשע, levar
miBilam harasha, except for בלעם, because he's the one non-Jew on the
list. I think that's presumably why. Hey, you can spend a lot
of time explicating how evil he was. דכמה דמשכחת ביה דרוש ביה,
Dechamah demishkachat bei derosh bei, as much as you can say or
to explicate and expound and say that he was evil, have a
ball. Okay. Now we're moving from בלעם to דואג, Doeg, דואג האדומי,
Doeg ha'Adomi, right? The one who told שאול Shaul that דוד David
was hiding in נוב עיר הכהנים, Nov ir hakohanim, wiped out and
so on, yes. So usually when you have a מין min approaching
somebody, right?
I said, it doesn't have the normal end that those stories normally
have. Yeah, I don't know what to say, although if you look
at it could be, I should check, anytime there's a מין min
thing it might be something that was was censored out if you
want to sort of check in the in the in the what
do you call it the שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz there. But yeah, other than
the possible hidden reference to Jesus, there's not exactly clear what this
has to do with a מין. min. All right. So anyway, it
says like this.
Okay, so now up to דואג. Doeg. Okay. So remember we'd always
start with a little play on the words of his name. כתיב
דואג וכתיב דויג, Ketiv Doeg vechetiv Doyeg, it's written... In one place
with
דלת וו יוד יוד גימל. dalet vav yod yod gimmel. אמר רבי
יוחנן מתחילה matchila היה הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu דואג doeg
שמא shema יצא yetze זה zeh לתרבות רעה letarbut ra'ah because דואג
Doeg you know was like this great wise person according to חז״ל,
Chazal, right, tremendous תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, all these amazing things. So
God was anxious because even though even when he was righteous God
sort of you know there's always the question about God knowing the
future and free will but God knew that there was always this
potential that he could go astray. So that's דואג. Doeg. לאחר שיצא
Lachar she-yatza and then once it actually actualized אמר אוי, oy, that's
דוי, Dovay, the וו יוד יוד, vav yod yod, woe שיצא זה.
she-yatza zeh. Woe that this person in the end was born even
though he was started his life so righteous or woe that he
left the good path and he went to the evil path. אמר
רבי יצחק Amar Rabbi Yitzchak מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant by
the verse מה תתהלל ברעה הגבור חסד אל כל היום, Mah tithallel
be-ra'ah ha-gibor chesed El kol hayom, חסד, chesed, right? Okay. מה תתהלל
Mah tithallel so מה תתהלל
ברעה mah tithallel be-ra'ah why will the why will the mighty person
like praise himself glorify himself with evil with evil
חסד אל כל היום chesed El kol hayom the kindness of God
the whole day? So what does that mean? אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך
הוא לדואג, Amar leih Hakadosh Baruch Hu le-Doeg, לא גבור בתורה אתה?
lo gibor ba-Torah atta? I don't understand how this happened to you.
Weren't you a great valorous person in תורה? Torah? מה תתהלל ברעה
Mah tithallel be-ra'ah why would why are you glorifying yourself in evil
what led you down this path? לא חסד אל נטוי עליך כל
היום? Lo chesed El natui alecha kol hayom? Didn't you have God's
kindness poured out to you stretched out to you the whole day
you know in terms of your learning of תורה Torah and you
were so successful and so on and you know serving God how
did you go how did you go off the path?
ואמר רבי יצחק Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv what's meant
by the verse ולרשע אמר אלהים מה לך לספר חקי? Vela-rasha amar
Elohim mah le-cha lesapper chukkai? So to the wicked person God says
what business do you have speaking of my of my edicts of
my laws. אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא לדואג הרשע Amar leih Hakadosh
Baruch Hu le-Doeg harasha מה לך לספר חקי mah le-cha lesapper chukkai
a חוצפה chutzpah you now you know that you you're teaching my
תורה. Torah. כשאתה מגיע Keshe-atta maggia לפרשת מרצחים le-parshat meratzchim let's say
you're going and you're learning מכות Makkot right and you're talking about
או סנהדרין o Sanhedrin and you're talking about all of the punishments
for the murderers okay how you think you're supposed to give שיעור
shiur on that after what you've done?
ופרשת מספרי לשון הרע U-parshat mesapprei lashon hara and then when you're
talking about לשון הרע lashon hara like where you know how can
you how can you teach my תורה? Torah? You are you know
you know which is now חז״ל Chazal which is a point that
we've seen before you know about these great kings or whatever here's
a commoner learning תורה Torah so sometimes it's a little bit to
like mitigate and show that people are complex but also it's just
to show that just learning תורה Torah doesn't make you a righteous
person. Here you could be extremely knowledgeable maybe you give a brilliant
שיעור shiur and you're a completely right you know a corrupt person
and you're not you don't live the messages of it. So you
know it's sort of like you know what's the פסוק כי שפתי
כהן ישמרו דעת ותורה יבקשו מפיהו כי מלאך ה׳ צבאות הוא. Ki
siftei kohen yishmeru da'at ve-Torah yevakshu mi-pihu ki malakh Hashem Tzeva'ot hu.
Right if
your
if your rabbi is like an angel of God then you can
learn תורה Torah from him. תורה Torah is just not an intellectual
pursuit it's about an you know the the rabbi is supposed to
be or the teacher is supposed to be an embodiment of what
תורה Torah is about a living example of what תורה Torah is
about. So given what you've done how how do you think you're
supposed to give a שיעור shiur on הלכות רציחה hilchot retzicha you
know? ופרשת מספרי לשון הרע U-parshat mesapprei lashon hara מה אתה
דורש בהם mah atta doresh bahem what what are you going to
explicate about them? ותשא בריתי עלי פיך Ve-tissa briti alei picha you
lift up my covenant on your mouth you know given that you
are such a like a contradiction to everything and anathema to everything
that it's about. אמר רבי אמי Amar Rabbi Ami אין תורתו של
דואג אלא משפתיו ולחוץ. ein Torato shel Doeg ela mi-sefatav u-lachutz. It
didn't transform him. It was only from the lips outward. Right so
he could teach תורה Torah but it was never it never pierced
into inside of him. It was only what he was saying it
was never about who he was. Or not I don't know if
this is all of the whole time after he sins maybe initially
it was and then he went off the path but anyway the
point here is that in theory you know you can have somebody
that gives a great שיעור shiur and is a you know and
is a disgusting person and is a complete anathema to whatever all
the תורה Torah is about. ואמר רבי
יצחק Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv what's meant by
the verse ויראו צדיקים וייראו Veyiru tzaddikim ve-yira'u ועליו ישחקו ve-alav yischaku
and on him they would
laugh. בתחילה ייראו Batchila yira'u initially they
they right I'm sorry first I'm sorry initially they feared they feared
that people would learn from the bad example of דואג Doeg because
here he was he was a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and maybe
he would lead people astray ולסוף ישחקו u-lesof yischaku and then when
he met his downfall they laughed because now they saw oh good
people won't learn from him. ואמר רבי יצחק Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak מאי
דכתיב mai de-chtiv what's meant by the verse right because that's the
other problem of course somebody could be a big תלמיד חכם Talmid
Chacham and they're not a good person he can lead other people
astray. מאי דכתיב Mai de-chtiv what's meant by the verse חיל בלע
ויקיאנו Chayil bala vayaki'ennu he swallowed you know great treasure whatever and
then he spit it up מבטנו יורשנו אל mibitno yorishennu El from
his innards God will like you
know drive him out. So what does that mean? אמר דוד לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא Amar David lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu רבונו של עולם
Ribono shel olam Master of the universe ימות דואג yamut Doeg דואג
Doeg should die for his evil. אמר ליה Amar leih חיל בלע
ויקיאנו. chayil bala vayaki'ennu. He swallowed a great force, like he's learned
a lot of Torah. I don't want to bring death upon him
until he spits it out, until he loses his Torah.
Okay. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, מביטנו יורישנו אל, Mibitno yorishenu El, God,
you do it. You make him like drive it out of his
stomach. You make him forget his Torah, if that's what it's going
to take for you to bring about his death. אמר רבי יצחק,
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse,
גם אל יתצך לנצח, gam El yitatzcha lanetzach, even God will crush
you forever? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לדוד, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu le-David,
נשי דואג לעלמא דאתי? neishai Doeg le-alma de-atei? I want Doeg to
get Olam Haba. Remember before there was an approach that said all
of these people have a חלק לעולם הבא chelek le-olam haba except
Bilam? And then it said if David complains, God will say like,
I'll make peace with David and Doeg, and David and Achitophel, these
are the two people, right, who caused David, who were obviously, you
know, foes of David. So here, this is saying that Doeg isn't
getting Olam Haba. But God still wants to give him Olam Haba,
but David is not happy with it.
אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, so David said to God,
גם אל יתצך לנצח, gam El yitatzcha lanetzach, God should crush you
forever, no, don't let him get Olam Haba.
מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the verse,
יחתך ויסחך
מאהל, yechat-cha ve-yisach-cha me-ohel, God shall cut you off and remove you
from the tent, ושרשך מארץ חיים סלה, ve-shoresh-cha me-eretz chayim sela, and
your root from the land of the living? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, לימרו שמעתא בי מדרשא משמיה, limru shma’ta bei
midrasha mishmeih, fine, you don't want him to get Olam Haba, but
what about his Torah? Let them at least say over Torah in
his name in the Beit Midrash. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, יחתך ויסחך
מאהל, yechat-cha ve-yisach-cha me-ohel, let him be cut off from the tent,
the tent of Torah. No, he shouldn't even be quoted in the
tent of Torah. וליהוו ליה בנין רבנן? Ve-leihavu lei banin rabanan? Okay,
but at least let his kids be תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. ושרשך
מארץ חיים סלה, Ve-shoresh-cha me-eretz chayim sela, let his root be cut
off from the land of the living. I know, right? And before
we learned, it said that even the בני בנים של נבוכדנצר benei
banim shel Nevuchadnezzar etc. So the question here is, who's right in
this argument? Is it clear that David is right? I mean David
has a very deep personal stake in this, right? He's the wronged
party. Maybe God is right, but God maybe has to concede to
David because David is like, you know, refusing to allow it. So
it's not exactly, I think the whole point is to express the
complexity of this issue, right? It's all, you know, the whole question,
right? Like, you know, what do you do about scientific findings that
were discovered through, you know, immoral types of things, right? So what
do you do about the Torah of an immoral man that's still
good Torah? You know, and does he deserve the credit of his
descendants? On the other hand, the descendants, why shouldn't the descendants be
תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, right? So I think this is here to
just embody that complexity. I don't think there's a clear sense of
whether David is right or God is right here. Okay.
ואמר
רבי יצחק, Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by
the verse, איה סופר איה שוקל איה סופר את המגדלים, ayeh sofer
ayeh shokel ayeh sofer et ha-migdalim, where is the counter, where is
the weigher, where is the one who counts the towers?
איה סופר, Ayeh sofer, once like Doeg went off the path, where
is the one שסופר כל אותיות שבתורה? she-sofer kol otiyot she-ba-Torah? He
was able to know all of the letters in the Torah. What
happened to his greatness? Or either how did he forget his Torah?
How did somebody with all that Torah go off the right path?
איה שוקל, Ayeh shokel, where's the one who weighs, ששוקל כל קלים
וחמורים שבתורה, she-shokel kol kalim va-chamurim she-ba-Torah, like קל וחומר, kal va-chomer,
light and heavy? He's able to do all these קל וחומרים. kal
va-chomerim. איה סופר את המגדלים, Ayeh sofer et ha-migdalim, who counts the
towers, שהיה סופר שלש מאות הלכות פסוקות במגדל הפורח באויר? she-hayah sofer
shalosh me’ot halachot psukot be-migdal ha-poreiach ba-avir? He could discuss 300 laws
about a castle floating in the air. We talk about making castles
in the sky, right, castles in the air. But anyway, but Rashi
has a couple of explanations what it means, but the best one
is that in אהלות Ohalos there's a discussion about a chest which
is a מגדל migdal and it's half inside the house and half
outside and it's exposed to the אויר. avir. And what happens if
there's a part of a dead body in it? And what does,
does the טומאה tumah go outside the house or inside the house?
Anyway, so he even knew the most complex הלכות. halachot. One of
the other things also you came across in Rashi. Right, exactly. אמר
רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Ami, ארבע מאה בעיי בעו דואג ואחיתופל במגדל
הפורח
באויר. arba me’ah ba’ei ba’u Doeg ve-Achitofel be-migdal ha-poreiach ba-avir. Now we're
going to bring in Achitophel as well. They were such amazing תלמידי
חכמים. talmidei chachamim. They before it was they had פסקן paskan 300
הלכות. halachot. Here, they could ask 400 questions about a מגדל הפורח
באויר. migdal ha-poreiach ba-avir. ולא איפשט להו חד. ve-lo ifshat lehu chad.
However, there's like a little undercutting, you know, it's easy to ask
questions. Before we said he had שלש מאות הלכות פסוקות, shalosh me’ot
halachot psukot, which means like he really came to a conclusion. Now
we're sort of stepping back a little bit. Yeah, they asked a
lot of questions, but they were only able to resolve one of
them. Okay, if you have that insertion there. אמר רב, Amar Rav,
minute. אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah, רבותא למבעי בעיי? rabuta le-mib’ei ba’ei?
Big deal! Is it a big deal to ask questions? Now in
this context you might say, like anybody can ask questions, it's about
coming to answers. But the other point that's being made is, is
that the point, the larger theme that was introduced earlier, which is
Torah scholarship is not the same as being a good person. Don't
go ahead spending all your time saying, oh my god, he was
such an amazing תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. It's like, you know what?
It's not all about Torah scholarship, okay? Because בשני דרב יהודה כולי
תנויי בנזיקין. bi-shnei de-Rav Yehudah kuli tanuyei bi-Nezikin. In the years of
Rav Yehudah, all they learned was נזיקין. Nezikin. That's what they did,
they did not learn the other five סדרים: sedarim: נשים, Nashim, מועד.
Moed. certainly not טהרות, Taharos, they just learned נזיקין. Nezikin. ואנן קמתנינא
טובא בעוקצין. Va'anan ka matninya tuva b'Uktzin.
We know even the most obscure stuff, we know even עוקצין, Uktzin,
which is this you know this obscure מסכת masechet in טהרות. Taharos.
Okay, וכי הוי מטי רב יהודה, v'chi havi mati Rav Yehuda, and
when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda would get to the משנה, Mishnah, this
is in טהרות, Taharos, not עוקצין, Uktzin, אשה שכבשה ירק בקדירה, isha
she'kevsha yerek b'kdeira, a woman who is like pickling a vegetable in
a pot, ואמרי לה זיתים שכבשן בטרפיהן טהורין, v'amri lah zeisim she'kevshan
b'tarfeihen tehorin,
or olives that are being pickled with their leaves, they're טהורין, tehorin,
whether the leaf communicates טומאה tumah or doesn't communicate טומאה, tumah, אמר
הויות דרב ושמואל קחזינא הכא. amar havayos d'Rav u'Shmuel k'chazina hacha.
So he said like, you know, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was the
student of שמואל, Shmuel he said like, oh, these are the types
of questions רב Rav and שמואל would ask, I have no idea
what the heck is going on. Okay, he was like completely clueless.
All he knew was סדר נזיקין. Seder Nezikin. ואנן קמתנינן בעוקצין תליסר
מתיבתא. va'anan ka matninan b'Uktzin tlissar mesivta.
And we have thirteen ישיבות, yeshivos, thirteen like, you know, major discussions
about this. And yet, nevertheless, so we're like, oh, we're much more
knowledgeable and we have a much greater breadth and depth, you know,
certainly breadth
than רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. Right, we don't have ירידת הדורות. yeridat
hadorot. And nevertheless, רב יהודה שלף מסאני ואתא מיטרא. Rav Yehuda shalyif
msanei v'ata mitra. All he had to do was take off his
shoe and it would rain when it was time when it was
praying for rain. ואנן, va'anan, right, just get ready to engage in
one of the symbols of like fasting. ואנן צבחינן, va'anan tzavchinan, we
pray and דאבן daven and yell the whole day, וליכא דמשגח בן,
v'leika d'mashgiach ban, and nobody pays attention to us.
אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא ליבא בעי, ela Hakadosh Baruch Hu liba ba'ei,
which is a little bit play in the word of ליביי בעי,
libay ba'ei, ליבא בעי. liba ba'ei. God doesn't want, you know, your
brilliant Talmudic questions, God wants, he's בעי, ba'ei, wants your heart. Right,
he wants the religious sincerity. So, you know, so again, mentioning that
they're big תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim is partly to make them more
complex figures, but it's partly also to say like, no, you know,
and as the point before, you can be teaching amazing שיעורים shiurim
and asking all these questions and like you have no right to
be doing it because ultimately it's about, you know, representing the תורה
Torah and having the תורה Torah transform you. Okay, דכתיב וה' יראה
ללבב, d'chtiv v'Hashem yireh lalevav, God sees to the heart. אמר רב
משרשיא דואג ואחיתופל לא הוו סברי שמעתא. amar Rav Mesharshiya Doeg v'Achitofel
lo havu savri shma'ata. So now, okay, that's one approach. Let them
be big תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Who cares? But others don't like
that, you know, don't like that, that's too incongruous. So he said,
you know what? They didn't really know how to learn. מתיב מר
זוטרא מאן דכתיב ביה, masiv Mar Zutra man d'chtiv beih, the one
of whom it's written, I don't know how we know it's written
about דואג, Doeg, איה סופר איה שוקל איה סופר את המגדלים, ayeh
sofer ayeh shokel ayeh sofer es hamigdalim, and you want to say
they didn't know how to understand what they were learning? Right, because
he doesn't want to have that kind of contradictory type of a
of a reality. אלא דלא הוו סלקי שמעתא אליבא דהלכתא. ela d'lo
havu salki shma'ata aliba d'hilchasa. No, so this is going back to
some of the tension before, which is they knew three hundred הלכה
פסוקות halacha psukos or they knew to ask questions but they didn't
know to come to conclusions. So that's what he said. Now, they
might have been big תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, but where did the
fact that they were not sort of true serving God, how did
that express itself in their תורה? Torah? It expressed itself in their
תורה Torah that if the תורה Torah was just like an intellectual
pursuit for them, because it wasn't true עבודת השם, avodas Hashem, they
didn't come to the right הלכה halachic conclusion. Okay, דכתיב סוד ה'
ליראיו. d'chtiv sod Hashem lireiaiv.
God speaks to those who fear him. So that's how it expresses
itself. So that's like a way of striking a balance. You could
be a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham if it's all intellectual game
for you, but unless it's עבודת השם, avodas Hashem, you're not going
to come to the right הלכה halachic conclusion. Let's just read one
more line. אמר רבי אמי לא מת דואג עד ששכח תלמודו. amar
Rabbi Ami lo mes Doeg ad she'shachach talmudo. Going back to the
story before. God says, let him, you know, God didn't want to
kill him until he forgot his learning. He didn't die until he
forgot his learning. שנאמר הוא ימות באין מוסר, shene'emar hu yamut b'ein
musar, he will die without מוסר, musar, without like, you know, instruction.
וברב אולתו ישגה, u'verov ivalto yishgeh, with his great foolishness he will
err. Okay. רב אשי אמר נצטרע, Rav Ashi amar nitztara, he became
a leper. שנאמר הצמתה כל זונה ממך, shene'emar hatzamta kol zona mimecha,
where you cut off all of the sort of prostitutes from you.
וכתיב התם לצמיתות, u'chtiv hasam l'tzmisus, and when it says the word
לצמיתות l'tzmisus in the תורה, Torah, which is about like the land
selling it for perpetuity, ומתרגמינן לחלוטין, u'metargminan l'chalutin, a חלוט chalut for
perpetuity. ותנן אין בין מוסגר ומוחלט אלא פריעה ופרימה. u'tnan ein bein
musgar u'muchlat ela priah u'frima. There's no difference between a leper who's
closed up and a leper who's a full leper, a full מצורע,
metzora, except for the rending of the garments and the growing of
the hair. So it's a whole big thing to get the word
הצמתה hatzamta
to refer to being a מצורע. metzora. Anyway, okay. And the פסוקים
pesukim are actually talking about דואג, Doeg, he was talking about something
else, right? Yeah, I don't even know. Anyway, one more line about
this. אמר רבי יוחנן שלושה מלאכי חבלה נזדמנו לו לדואג. amar Rabbi
Yochanan shlosha malachei chavala nizdamnu lo l'Doeg. Three angels of destruction approached
דואג. Doeg. אחד ששיכח תלמודו, echad she'shikach talmudo, one made him forget
his learning. ואחד ששרף נשמתו, v'echad she'saraf nishmato, burned his soul. ואחד
שפיזר אפרו בבתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות. v'echad she'pizer afro b'vattei khnesiyos u'vattei
midrashos. Okay, which is presumably how he gets some presence in the
בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, I'm assuming. His ashes are there. Okay, so
he gets some presence in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. Okay. So
we will end with this. A little bit of ברכה. I guess
so. Okay, fine. We'll end with that. To be continued tomorrow.